{"tossups": [{"question": "During the Depression, this state sold the rights to its Spiro Mounds to artifact-hunters. The 1898 Curtis Act expropriated millions of acres of land in this state. In an 1887 election, one region of this state was to become the state of Cimarron. After the passage of the Indian Removal Act of 1830, members of the Five Civilized Tribes were moved to territory in this modern-day state. The \u201cBoomers\u201d and \u201cSooners\u201dsettled, for the point, what Great Plains state heavily struck by the Dust Bowl near cities like Tulsa?", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A news anchor at this event apologized for reporting while out of breath, as a security guard \u201cput [him] on the deck.\u201d Pigasus was supported at this event by the Yippies. This event prompted Walter Cronkite to say, \u201cI think we are dealing with a bunch of thugs here.\u201d After this event, it was noted that\u201cMcGovern wouldn\u2019t have used Gestapo tactics.\u201d TV cameras covering this event alternated between police macing protesters and celebrations after Hubert Humphrey\u2019s nomination. For the point, name this highly contested political convention in Chicago.", "answer": "19<b>68 Democratic National Convention</b> (or 19<b>68 DNC</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Alongside Demetrius and Chalcis, one of Macedon\u2019s Three Fetters was located in the citadel of this city. This city\u2019s name entered Greek lexicon as a verb meaning \u201cto have sex\u201d due to prostitute priestesses at a temple to Aphrodite outside this city. This city was burned to the ground after its capture by Romans under Lucius Mummius, and gives its name to a league created by Phillip II of Macedon. For the point, name this Greek city, located on a namesake isthmus between the Peloponnese and Athens.", "answer": "<b> Corinth</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This ruler ordered Stephen Tomasevic executed at the Emperor\u2019s Field during his conquest of Bosnia. This ruler was targeted by Vlad the Impaler\u2019s night attack at Targoviste. This ruler\u2019s most famous military conquest required transporting galleys overland to avoid a boom chain across the Golden Horn and led to the death of Constantine XI Palaiologos. For the point, name this sultan of the Ottoman Empire who had the Hagia Sophia renovated and converted into a mosque after he conquered Constantinople.", "answer": "<b> Mehmet the Conqueror</b> (or<b> Mehmed II</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a photograph of this player, Joe Garagiola looks out of the centerfield clubhouse as this player is about to turn Vic Wertz\u2019s fly ball into an over-the-shoulder catch. The all-time record for putouts by an outfielder is held by this man. This godfather of Barry Bonds made \u201cthe Catch\u201d in the 1954 World Series and is tied with Hank Aaron and Stan Musial for most All-Star Games played. For the point, name this\u201cSay Hey Kid\u201d who played center field for the Giants from 1951 to 1972 and hit 660 career home runs.", "answer": "Willie Howard<b> Mays</b> Jr Page 1", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Shuttle diplomacy was used in the making of this agreement, which failed to address the \u201cright of return.\u201d This agreement, which paved the way for the future Oslo Accords, called for freedom of passage in the Straits of Tiran and Suez Canal. The Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to two signatories of this agreement, Menachem Begin and Anwar Sadat. For the point, name this agreement between Egypt and Israel that was brokered by Jimmy Carter.", "answer": "<b> Camp David Accord</b>s", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The diary of Tanya Savicheva documents this event, noting on its last pages that \u201ceveryone died. Only Tanya is left.\u201d The Sinyavino Offensive unsuccessfully attempted to relieve this event. One participant in this event was successfully contained by the Karelia fortified region, and one side was supplied by the Ice Road during the winter, with trucks crossing the frozen surface of Lake Ladoga. Bombardment and starvation killed over a million Soviet citizens in, for the point, what 872 day Nazi siege of what is now St. Petersburg?", "answer": "Siege of<b> Leningrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This character allies with Tullus Aufidius shortly after noting \u201cMy birthplace hate I, and my love\u2019s upon / this enemy town\u201d in an Act Four soliloquy. This character\u2019s mother, Volumnia, kneels before this man, who cries \u201cYou have won a happy victory for Rome, but for your son...most mortal to him!\u201d For the point, name this Roman general who led the Volsci in a stopped siege on Rome and whose story was told in one of Shakespeare\u2019s final tragedies.", "answer": "Gaius Marcius<b> Coriolanus</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "Early in his career, this man\u2019s oration prompted a riot in Pendleton, Indiana in which he permanently maimed his hand. Hugh Auld collected this man\u2019s wages during his time as a caulker in Baltimore. This frequent collaborator with Gerrit Smith ran with Victoria Woodhull on the Equal Rights Party presidential ticket in 1872. This supporter of the Seneca Falls Convention published three autobiographies, including<em> My Bondage and My Freedom</em>. For the point, name this founder of the newspaper<em> The North</em> <em>Star</em>, a former slave turned abolitionist.", "answer": "Frederick<b> Douglass</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This politician referred to opponent William Randolph Hearst as \u201ca man as low and mean as I can picture.\u201d Along with his so-called political \u201ctwin,\u201d Robert F. Wagner, this man chaired the commission that investigated the Triangle Shirtwaist fire. Known as the \u201cHappy Warrior,\u201d he broke with his successor as governor, Franklin Roosevelt, and opposed the New Deal. For the point, what New York Governor was the first Catholic nominee for President, but lost to Herbert Hoover?", "answer": "Alfred \u201cAl\u201d<b> Smith</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, Vasile Malutan\u2019s request for two helicopters was denied with a unit commander replying, \u201cYou are on your own...good luck!\u201d The aftermath of this event led to the formation of the National Salvation Front. It began after Pastor Laszlo Tokes\u2019 criticism of a nation\u2019s \u201cSystemization\u201dpolicy led to his eviction from a church in Timisoara. This event culminated in a Christmas Day execution of a nation\u2019s leader and wife Elena on live television. For the point, name this 1989 event in which Nicolae Ceausescu [cho-CHESS-koo] was overthrown.", "answer": "1989<b> Romanian Revolution</b> (accept<b> execution</b> of Nicolae<b> Ceausescu</b> before \u201cexecution\u201dis read; accept<b> overthrow</b> of Nicolae<b> Ceausescu</b> before \u201cNicolae\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man observed that the \u201caccumulation of navies\u201d was \u201cmeant for us, they can be meant for no other\u201d and visualized clanking chains on the fields of Boston. This man was interrupted by accusations of treason after asserting that \u201cCaesar had his Brutus, and Charles I his Cromwell.\u201d He declined to attend the Constitutional Convention, claiming that he \u201csmelt a rat in Philadelphia\u201d. For the point, name this Founding Father who, in 1775, declared to the Virginia Convention that \u201cI know not what course others may take, but as for me, give me liberty or give me death.\u201d", "answer": "Patrick<b> Henry</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The loser of this battle blamed his wife for circumventing his protective magic charms. A decisive charge from Joseph Daveiss\u2019s dragoons helped conclude this battle, in which Spier Spencer\u2019s Yellow Jackets joined the winning side beforehand. Prophetstown was burned in the aftermath of this defeat for Tenskatawa, the brother of Tecumseh. For the point, name this battle in the War of 1812 whose legacy was used in the presidential campaign of its winning general, William Henry Harrison.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tippecanoe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One type of these objects, the trace italienne, featured a low glacis [glah-see]. Ravelins and tenailles [tehn-aye] could be added to increase the efficacy of these objects. The theory of the construction of these things was the specialty of Marshal Vauban. The medieval enceinte [ohn-sahnt] were one type of these constructs, which can be supported by redoubts and are often accompanied by breastworks and ditches. For the point, name this defensive structure that comes in star and bastion varieties.", "answer": "<b> fort</b>ifications (prompt on defensive structure; do not accept or prompt on castle)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This politician advocated for the Moreland Act after defeating William Randolph Hearst to become the Governor of New York. He oversaw the Washington Naval Conference while serving as Warren Harding\u2019s Secretary of State. This man\u2019s presidential run was defeated by a candidate who used the slogan \u201cHe Kept Us Out of War.\u201d While serving as Chief Justice, this man\u2019s court ruled the NIRA and AAA unconstitutional in<em> U.S. v. Butler</em> and<em> U.S. v. Schechter</em>. For the point, name this loser of the 1916 presidential election who later became Chief Justice during the New Deal Era.", "answer": "Charles Evans<b> Hughes</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state was the only one to protest the signing the 1949 Basic Law, but agreed to follow it anyway. One war to prevent Hapsburg annexation of this state was derisively called the War of the Potatoes. One king of this state, ruled by the Wittelsbachs, was declared mad due to his artistic patronage, including supporting Richard Wagner and building Neuscwhanstein [noysh-von-shtein] Castle. Ludwig II was king of, for the point, what largest German state whose capital is Munich?", "answer": "<b> Bavaria</b> (or<b> Bayern</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In one work, crowds shout \u201cGlory!\u201d as this man passes by after taking power. Later in that work, this man is compared to Herod by a holy fool who sings \u201cFlow, flow, bitter tears!\u201d at the end of the opera. This man is warned by Prince Shuysky that a pretender by the name of Dmitri has risen in Lithuania. For the point, name this boyar, the subject of a Pushkin play and Mussorgsky opera that are both set during Russia\u2019s Time of Troubles.", "answer": "Boris (Fyodorovich)<b> Godunov</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "This party entered a 1977 coalition with David Steel\u2019s party. One newspaper ran a cover asking the last person leaving the country to \u201cturn out the lights\u201d if this party won. Under James Callaghan, this party lost popularity due to the Winter of Discontent. This party established the National Health Service under Prime Minister Clement Attlee and promoted the \u201cThird Way\u201d under the leadership of Tony Blair. For the point, name this opposition party in the current House of Commons currently led by Jeremy Corbyn.", "answer": "<b> Labour</b> Party of the United Kingdom (or England or Great Britain) Page 5", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s pet cat \u201crocks the Hill\u201d in an unreleased platforming game. He performed \u201cHeartbreak Hotel\u201d and \u201cGod Bless the Child\u201d on the Arsenio Hall Show, and used Fleetwood Mac\u2019s \u201cDon\u2019t Stop (Thinking About Tomorrow)\u201d as his campaign song. During that same campaign, he rebuked a comment made by Sister Souljah and was hailed by Toni Morrison as \u201cthe first black president\u201d. For the point, name this owner of Socks the Cat and saxophonist who won the 1992 election for President.", "answer": "William Jefferson \u201cBill\u201d<b> Clinton</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A treaty with this government ended Britain\u2019s Splendid Isolation. The Triple Invention targeted this government, leading to the Persevering Through Hardship movement. This government waged war with the Republic of Ezo, which formed after this government\u2019s victory in the Boshin War. The Charter Oath was created by the leader of this government, who aimed to restore imperial authority. For the point, name this late 19th century Japanese government that succeeded the Tokugawa Shogunate.", "answer": "<b> Meiji</b> government (accept any additional information with<b> Meiji</b>, like \u201crestoration\u201d or\u201coligarchy;\u201d prompt on Government of Japan; prompt on Japan)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s second wife, Eliza Jumel, left him after four months of marriage; their divorce was finalized on the day this man died. James Wilkinson exposed this man\u2019s plot to lodge war against Mexico and seize part of the Louisiana Purchase. A political party tried, but failed, to name this man on all but one of their electoral ballots; instead, this man tied with his running mate, Thomas Jefferson, in the election of 1800. For the point, name this third U.S. vice president, today best known as the duelist who killed Alexander Hamilton.", "answer": "Aaron<b> Burr</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man is shown with his right arm outstretched in<em> The Distribution of the Eagle Standards</em>. He is shown in ermine in a portrait whose pose references the Statue of Zeus, and is also the subject of a five-version oil painting in which he wears a red cape atop a rearing horse, crossing the Alps. In a work set at Notre Dame, Pope Pius VII watches this man perform the title action on himself. For the point, name this man whom Jacques-Louis David [dah-veed] depicted being crowned as Emperor of the French.", "answer": "<b> Napol\u00b4eon Bonaparte</b> (accept either)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Vinayak Savarkar was falsely accused of perpetrating this event, which led to the RSS party being banned for a period of time. A little girl tried to stop the perpetrator of this event, which took place at the Birla House, by telling him that \u201cBapu is already late.\u201d In its aftermath, the sitting prime minister announced that \u201cthe light has gone out of our lives.\u201d Nathuram Godse was hanged for committing, for the point, what 1948 murder of an Indian nonviolence activist?", "answer": "<b> Assassination</b> (or<b> killing</b>, etc.) of<b> M</b>ahatma (or<b> M</b>ohandas)<b> Gandhi</b> (prompt on partial answers; do not accept mentions of Indira or Rajiv Gandhi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One son of Ceuthonymus guards the cattle of this figure, who turned one of his lovers into a white poplar tree. Served by Menoetes, this god was also known as \u201cthe Rich One\u201d due to his association with precious metals. The Romans syncretized this god with Dis Pater. This god\u2019s helm helped Perseus escape the Gorgons, and the guard to his realm was placated by barley cake. For the point, name this Greek god who abducted Persephone and brought her to the underworld.", "answer": "<b> Hades</b> (accept<b> Aides</b> or<b> Aidoneus</b>; accept<b> Pluto</b> or<b> Plouton</b> until \u201cGreek\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Alberic of Trois-Fontaines described this organization as the \u201corder of bearded brethren.\u201dThis organization was created at the Council of Nabulus by Baldwin II, who appointed its first Grandmaster, Hugues de Payens. Phillip IV forced the Avignon Pope, Clement V, to order the arrest of all members of this organization, leading to the death of its final Grandmaster, Jacques de Molay. For the point, name this Christian military order, originally created to protect Christian pilgrimages to the Holy Land, that wore a uniform adorned with a red cross.", "answer": "Knights<b> Templar</b> (or the<b> Poor Fellow-Soldiers of Christ and the Temple of Solomon</b>; accept the<b> Order of Solomon\u2019s Temple</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}